Right so what we call immediate RL immediate
reinforcement learning problems so if you
remember I said there are many, many characteristics
of a reinforcement learning problem and one
of those was that you get this evaluation
from the environment it could potentially
be delayed right so I said you might actually
lose a piece very important piece in the middle
of a chess game but you get a reward only
at the end it is not like the final move you
made is the one that causes you to lose it
could be somewhere along the way right.
So what we are going to do now is to actually
consider a much simpler version of the problem
where we do not have this the temporal nature
to it right, so we are not we are not going
to assume that the rewards are the scalar
evaluation that comes from the environment
is going to come at a farther time than when
the action is actually performed right so
I am going to assume that as soon as you perform
an action like you are going to get a evaluation
right and that is it basically right.
So we are going to consider a much more simplified
version of the problem that is at every time
instance I am required to pick an action right,
so at every time instant t right I pick an
action At right, and then I receive a reward
Rt and that is it.
my interaction is ended right.
So I can learn something from this interaction
and go back and pick another action at time
t plus 1 right so that is why we call this
immediate reinforcement learning problems
because the outcome is immediate so as soon
as I take an action I get a reward right.
So what else is missing in my description
here there is no real input to the system
right there is no state signal that the system
is seeing so all the input that it is getting
are the rewards right there is no state input
to the system right, so it is like it's just
solving the same problem again and again right
so instead of thinking of it as not having
a state you could think of it as having like
every time I give it the same input and I
am asking you to give me a action in response
to that does this seem like a reasonable thing
to have can you think of cases where this
might actually be an appropriate model.
So one example which people give is in drug
testing right so I have I have a certain symptom
that is presented to me right and I can choose
on one of four different drugs to treat that
symptom right so I first I give drug one it
may or may not cure the person if it cures
the person then I get a reward if it doesn’t
cure a person I do not get a reward right
but it could very well be that for a variety
of reasons the person did not get cured it
is not because that the drug one was not the
right drug to give for this person right.
For this symptoms but for a variety of other
reasons the patient might not have been cured
so I cannot conclude by just administering
the drug once that the drug is ineffective
for a set of symptoms right I have to keep
trying the drug multiple times right before
I can come to a conclusion that the drug is
ineffective for a person correct right so
for a certain set of symptoms so it is like
saying that okay there are multiple you know
samples that I have in a lab and each of them
is exhibiting the same disease.
Let us not talk about human beings administering
drugs and killing them or something can think
of what samples in the lab right I'm going
to add some drugs to that and see if that
particular organism dies right in that in
the when I add the drug right so it is essentially
the same presentation as far as the drug testing
is goes right it is the same organism that
I am trying to kill say microorganism that
I am trying to kill across all of these different
instances it is like the same state that is
being presented to me over and over again
but then I have multiple choices that I could
make and as soon as I do the choice I get
a feedback saying okay.
Yeah the organism died or it didn’t die
right, so I have to keep trying this multiple
before I figure out which is the right drug
to administer okay good is it clear so that
gives you an example right so there are a
couple of things which I kind of rolled into
that example as well so one of those is that
the outcome can be stochastic right, so every
time I take an action right so I need not
be given the same evaluation back right so
I take a tissue sample add a drug to it right
so i might not succeed every time right so
sometimes I will succeed sometimes I might
not succeed so there is some kind of a stochastic
nature to the outcome right.
So as a consequence of the stochastic nature
what did you have to do I had to repeat things
multiple times right so this is these are
things which you have to keep in mind when
we are talking about this kind of immediate
reinforcement learning problems that we are
going to have stochastic outcomes and then
we have to think about repeating choices multiple
times before we can be sure of the outcome
right is there anything else that was that
would have been critical to the successful
outcome of this let us say that I tried drug
one okay.
And the organism survived okay, so then I
just can I keep using drug one for all the
other organisms as well let us say let us
keep the problem simplified right I just will
say have only two drugs drug one drug two
okay I take the first organism give it drug
one it survives I take the second organism
give it drug two does not survive okay, now
can I conclude that which one is more effective
drug one or drug two we don’t know I am
assuming is ones is survival what we are looking
for not survival well what we are looking
for not survival talking about microorganisms
here right I actually flipped it around but
nobody actually noticed it.
So yeah so I am looking for non survival of
the microorganism right so in this case drug
two appeared to be more effective than drug
one right so that does not mean I can keep
giving drug two to all the other samples right
I need to actually go back and try drug one
a few times right so this is the exploration
right I was telling you about exploration
in the previous class right this is the exploration
here that I have to do exploration so the
critical thing here that even the simple case
of this immediate reinforcement learning introduces
to is the need for exploration right but can
I just keep exploring can I just keep giving
random drugs to each of those samples right
at some point I have to stop right.
I am interested actually in killing those
microorganisms right at some point I have
to stop and decide okay here this is the actual
drug that is going to kill the microorganism
and I have to start giving that drug right
this need not be an explicit point where I
stop we will see as we go along but I am interested
in eventually exploiting the knowledge that
I am acquiring about this the whole system
right, so either I explore or I have to at
some point I have to stop and start exploiting
so there is this inherent tension between
exploration and exploitation okay.
They are in some sense at loggerheads with
each other right if I stop at some point and
say okay I have know enough about the system
and then I start exploiting then I necessarily
have to stop my exploration right but then
if I do not explore enough I will be exploiting
a poor solution right so this exploration
exploitation so sometimes people call it a
conflict sometimes it is called the called
the Explore exploit dilemma right so should
I explore or should I exploit so that is essentially
what this immediate reinforcement learning
problems captures for us okay.
Since this is a very crucial question in reinforcement
learning so we will look at this immediate
reinforcement learning problems in a little
bit of detail so that it will motivate some
of the other things that we will do later
when we move to the full RL problem right
and so what I will do which is slightly different
from what is there in the textbook, so how
many of you have actually looked at the textbook
good see I did not ask how many of you have
read the book right.
So what I will do is slightly different from
the book and I am still not decided whether
it will be for both versions of the course
let us talk a little bit more about some of
the theoretical questions that people are
interested in addressing in the immediate
RL setting right.
The book just gives you a very very algorithmic
very prescriptive viewpoint of this right
this is oh here is how you solve the immediate
reinforcement learning problem right it does
not go beyond that it does not give you anything
about right so why do people solve it the
way they do it right I will go a little bit
beyond that and try to give you some intuition
in that mainly because that seems to be a
very active area of research nowadays in reinforcement
learning and many of the ideas that people
are using there are also being transferred
to the full reinforcement learning setting.
The one with all the delayed rewards the states
and things like that right so lot of ideas
from the research in this immediate RL setting
is also being used in the full RL setting
so I want to introduce you to those topics
right, yeah so despite the makeup of the class
right which is predominantly undergrad this
is a graduate level course right so I want
you to want to introduce people to research
questions and other things there have been
demands for I to actually teach an advanced
RL course at some point I know at least one
person who'll take it I am going to try this.
Now every class I am going to make people
turn and look at you at least once I managed
to do that last class anyway so go back so
we will look at a little bit of formalism
on this right so what I am going to assume
is that I have a set of actions A which I
will index by 1 to n so action one could be
anything right and I am just giving arbitrary
numbers 1 to n it could be drug one drug two
drug three right or it could be ad one ad
two ad three whatever it is just 1 to n is
what we will denote it as right.
And each action when I pick that action right
gets a payoff it is an evaluation so I am
going to be using these terms interchangeably
right reward payoff evaluation cost so all
of this denote the same thing that dotted
line that came in my box diagram right so
depending on what literature you come from
you use different different names for it right
so the reward typically comes from guess psychology
right cost comes from control theory optimization
yeah payoff comes from econ economics and
what is the last thing I said evaluation comes
from optimization okay fine.
So depending on which, which background you
come from you give it different names right
and so I will use them interchangeably for
example for most of this literature I will
be using payoffs because a lot of the work
has been done in the in the OR and Economics
community in when they are trying to analyze
these kinds of problems right so when you
pull each when I actually select an arm I
select an action right what's going to happen
is that I will get a reward or a payoff sampled
from some unknown distribution so what do
I mean by that stochastic but what do I mean
more I mean it can right this is something
which I found people have difficulty so some
people at least have difficulty when I say
it is sampled from a distribution so what
I mean by mean is the following.
Let us keep it simple so that people can conceptualize
it so associated with each action let us say
that I have a coin associated with each action
there is a coin okay that has some probability
of coming up heads and some probability of
coming up tails okay so let some probability
P of coming up heads lets say I pick action
one then there is a probability P1 of coming
up heads when I toss the coin right and I
will say that if the coin comes up heads ok
I will give you a payoff of 1 if the coin
comes up tails I will give you a payoff of
0 right.
So every time I select an action I am going
to toss this coin so depending on whether
it comes up heads or tails I will give you
either a one or a zero right so the payoff
that I will get every time I select that action
is not the same right but what is same the
coin right if I select actual action one I
will always toss coin one if I select action
5 and always toss coin five right I am not
changing these coins okay, is it clear does
it make sense to people right I will not change
the coins the coins will be the same right.
But every time I pick an action I will toss
that coin and I will give you the payoff or
reward corresponding to the outcome of the
coin toss okay so if I say that the probability
of reward for picking action 1 is 0.8 what
does it mean the probability of heads of the
associated coin is point eight right in this
case I can go further I can also say something
else I can say that the expected payoff of
picking action one is point eight as well
right because the probability point eight
I will get a reward of 1 with the probability
point 2 I will get a reward of 0 so if I take
the expectation of this it will get will be
point eight right.
So people understand this now so when I say
select an arm select an action I will tell
you why I keep calling arm in a second and
then I will keep calling it arm so when I
select an action right then I am going to
toss a coin right depending on the outcome
of the coin I am going to give you reward
this is something which you should remember
when you are actually going and implementing
these things right so I had people do all
kinds of weird things right and make sure
that you remember what I mean when I say you
sample from a distribution okay great.
So now I gave you the simple example of tossing
a coin I could actually have any complex distribution
right so if a toss a coin what is the distribution
I am sampling from?
Bernoulli right I could have other kinds of
distributions I could have a Gaussian distribution
let us say so now what does it mean for every
action I choose okay.
So for action 1 there is going to be a like
some kind of a Gaussian distribution right
and so what is the axis here x axis here the
payoff the payoff or the reward x axis is
the payoff or the reward and the y axis is
the probability that you will see such a payoff
right so that is the most probable pay off
as it also happens to be the for Gaussians
this also happens to be the expected payoff
right so how will I sample from a Gaussian
pick a random number and 0 and anyone else
how do I sample from a Gaussian okay.
How do you do that people who are in my minor
I told you how to do this in the class okay
little bit more efficient way of doing it
yeah and then what you do?
Do not tell me you use Matlab no man it is
you know too many terminology you just keep
throwing them around what does MC stand for
in, Markov Chain, then there are two MCs then
you just told me a Monte Carlo I said give
me something more efficient and then you keep
saying another Monte Carlo method what is
this no one oh come on, fine okay Pallavi
you tell me, so the guys who were in the you
guys were there in my minor thing right I
actually told you how to sample do you remember
I said so I did this with a discrete distribution
and then I told you how to do this with continuous
distributions as well can you give them a
write-up on moodle okay.
So basically the idea is you generate a random
number right between 0 and 1 generate a uniform
random number between 0 and 1 right and then
keep integrating the area under the curve
what is it called the CDF right and then when
the CDF reaches that random number you generate
so that is the number you sample does it make
sense, so this is a complete aside.
(Refer Slide Time: 19:24)
Let us say that I have four possible outcomes
right I want to generate one of those four
outcomes at random right so the probabilities
are p1 p2 p3 p4 how will I do that I will
generate a uniform random number between 0
to 1 right, now so I will see if the number
is less than P1 if the number is less than
P1 I will generate outcome 1 if the number
is between p1 and p2 and generate the outcome
of two this number is between p2 and p3 l
generate the outcome of three generate number
is between p3 and p4 is it correct or wrong,
it should be between p1 and p1 plus p2 okay
it should be between p1 plus p2 and p1 plus
p2 plus p3 so it should be the cumulative
sum right it should be the cumulative sum
previous cumulative sum and the next cumulative
sum.
So if it lies between that then that is the
outcome right so if it is less than P1 I will
generate one if it is between p1 and p1 plus
p2 I will generate two if it is between p1
plus p2 and p1 plus p2 plus p3 I will generate
three if it is between p1 plus p2 plus p3
and 1 I will generate four right do not tell
me if p1 plus p2 plus p3 plus p4, so you can
simulate the CDF for the Gaussian right yeah
so there are ways of doing it right so there
we have doing this so you can do this for
any probability distribution for which you
can define the CDF.
Not just Gaussian it's not just discrete so
the discrete case it is very clear right so
what you are doing is essentially adding up
the probability so whenever you hit that number
you say that is the sample that you have drawn
right in this case you just do this for the
Gaussians okay so this is what I mean when
I say sample from a probability distribution
again it is not the most probable outcome
like when I say sample from this Gaussian
I have actually seen people implement okay
that’s the reason I keep reiterating this
people actually form the Gaussian and then
keep returning the value that has the highest
probability right.
So please do not do that of course if you
are using MATLAB or something like that you
don't even have to think about it we can just
say rand N and then it will give you a sample
from a normal distribution which is what Subho
was going to tell you is the way to sample
from a Gaussian but this is what it does internally
right and to give you the sample having said
this now you can go back to using randn yeah
you had a question okay fine so going back
associated with each of these actions right
I am going to have some distribution from
which the payoff is being sampled okay is
it clear.
And these distributions I am going to assume
at least initially will be fixed for the duration
of the experiment for duration of the learning
this distributions will be fixed like I said
you do not change the coin you don't change
the Gaussians also okay now if I knew the
Gaussians or if I knew the coin if I knew
the probability with which the coin will turn
up tails heads right so how will I solve the
problem there is no problem right I just picked
the action that has the highest mean right
highest mean and for the Gaussian or the highest
p1 for the coins right whatever it is the
highest expected payoff I just picked that
arm picked that action right.
So the challenge comes when I do not know
the distributions all I know is there is some
distribution which I am assuming is fixed
according to which the payoffs are generated
I do not know the distribution so I basically
have to figure out the distribution and then
pick the pick the action I picked action corresponding
to that right so is that clear so for each
of these actions right for each of these actions
I am going to assume that there is a true
expected payoff which we will denoted by q
star of A.
Let us say it's action so q star is a function
that will give me the true expected payoff
of action a right so in the case of the coins
q star of one will give me p1 which is the
probability of heads right q star of 2 will
give me p2 and so on so forth in the case
of Gaussians q star of one will give me mu
1 right q star of 2 will give mu 2 and so
on so forth so that’s essentially what the
q star function is this is again unknown to
me right if I know q star I am done right
I mean the problem is solved right but this
is the assumption we are going to make so
we have a set of actions A and we have a set
corresponding q stars that we do not know
about right.